<lesson>
<title>What are runes?</title>
<id>what_are_runes</id>
<body>Runes are an <b>alphabetic writing system</b>, popularly (and for the most part, correctly) associated with Scandinavian culture and with the Viking Age (c. 750-1050).

Though in principle runes may be used to write in any language, they are best suited to record the sounds of old Germanic tongues.

Unlike other European scripts (roman or greek alphabets, cyrillic letters), runes are an <b>epigraphic</b> script. In other words, they were normally carved into stone, wood, metal or bone, rather than written on paper. Of course, runic manuscripts do exist, but they were produced later, from historical curiosity.

<img src="image_gardby_runsten">Runestones were often raised to commemorate deceased family members</img>

It is important to emphasize that there wasn't a single canonical runic alphabet and the scripts varied depending on both geographical and temporal dimensions.

Commonly, four main types of rune row are distinguished: <b>the older fuþark, the Anglo-Frisian fuþorc, the younger fuþark and the medieval fuþork</b>. They differed in the number of symbols, complexity and the set of expressible sounds. Even within these four types, countless local variations are found.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Futhark? Fuþark? Fuþork?</title>
<id>futhark_meaning</id>
<body><b><i>Futhark, fuþark, fuþork...</i></b> what <i>are</i> those?

As you probably know very well, the word <i>alphabet</i> originates from the first two letters of the latin alphabet: <i>alpha (α)</i> and <i>beta (β)</i>.

It's exactly the same story with the runic alphabets. The name <i>futhark</i> comes from the first six runes in the rune row: <b>ᚠ (f), ᚢ (u), ᚦ (þ/th), ᚨ (a), ᚱ (r), ᚲ (k)</b>. As you can see, <i>futhark</i> and <i>fuþark</i> are different renderings, depending on how one chooses to read the Thorn rune (ᚦ).

<i>Fuþorc</i> is a rendering of the first characters of the <b>Anglo-Frisian</b> rune row (<b>ᚠᚢᚦᚩᚱᚳ</b>), and <i>fuþork</i> of the so-called (Scandinavian) medieval rune row (<b>ᚠᚢᚦᚮᚱᚴ</b>).

<img src="learn_futhark_6_runes">Comparison of first 6 runes</img>

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Transliteration</title>
<id>transliteration</id>
<body>Runic inscriptions are often presented in <b>transliteration</b>.

Every rune is assigned a corresponding letter from modern alphabet, generally roman, but also regional European letters as well as IPA characters are used.

Let us start with an example - the model for transliterating the older fuþark:

<img src="learn_older_futhark">The older <i>fuþark</i></img>

The modern equivalents for runic characters are generally chosen based on supposed sound value, but scholars accept that perfect phonetic reproduction of Viking Age language is impossible. Moreover, one rune can denote multiple sounds. For example: <i>ᚢ</i> may stand for <i>u</i>, <i>v</i>, and others, depending on the context.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Sound values</title>
<id>sound_values</id>
<body>Throughout the exercises and lessons as well you will see not only new rune characters, but likely also many latin-derived letters that may be new for you.

This lesson will equip you with some intuition how to read them.

<b>þ</b> denotes <i>[θ̠]</i>, the consonant sound of English <i><b>th</b>ink, me<b>th</b>od, pa<b>th</b></i>.
<b>æ, ä</b> is something like the vowel in English <i>c<b>a</b>t</i>.
<b>ŋ</b> stands for the final sound in southern English <i>si<b>ng</b></i>.
<b>ø, ö, œ</b> is the sound in French <i>p<b>eu</b>ple</i> or German <i>sch<b>ö</b>n</i>.
<b>ã</b> is a nasalized sound in French <i>d<b>an</b>se</i>.
<b>ð</b> is the consonant sound in English <i><b>th</b>en, fa<b>th</b>er</i>.

Note that we don't know for certain the exact sound values for different runes and the transliterations should never be interpreted as the correct way to pronounce the inscription. For example, while <i>ø</i> and <i>œ</i> denote the same sound in modern alphabets, runologists use them separately to denote runes with similar, but possibly not identical pronunciation.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Where did runes come from?</title>
<id>origins</id>
<body>The oldest known runic writings date back to at least the second century AD.

The earliest documented runic artifacts generally come from the area of modern Denmark, southern Norway and southern Sweden, however a number has been also found in northern Germany and eastern Europe.

The development of the runes was most likely influenced by contacts with the Roman Empire. Scholars have also emphasized striking similarities between the runic and other Mediterranean writing systems (Phoenician, Greek, Etruscan). Observation of literary societies inspired Germanic speakers to imitate this form of communication.

Despite developing their own writing system, the Germanic people cultivated mainly oral traditions for many centuries to come and never succeeded in introducing a wide-scale literacy (or perhaps never intended to). The first inscriptions were extremely laconic and consisted chiefly of names.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>The older fuþark</title>
<id>the_older_futhark</id>
<body>The <b>older fuþark</b> is the oldest known rune row. We say <b>rune row</b> somewhat interchangeably with <i>alphabet</i>, but also to stress the differences between rune rows and Greek and Roman alphabets. The order of the symbols is completely different from the Mediterranean alphabets, though the reason for this phenomenon is not known for sure.

<img src="learn_older_futhark">The older <i>fuþark</i></img>

We know the order from a number of rune-row inscriptions dated to 5th and 6th centuries. From 11 such inscriptions, only 4 contain the complete older fuþark. One of them is presented below:

<img src="image_kylverstone">The Kylver stone (held in Historiska Museet in Stockholm) depicts the complete older fuþark.</img>

The fuþark was also sometimes divided into three groups of eight symbols, these groups being called <b><i>ættir</i></b> in later Icelandic manuscripts. We don't know the reason for this division, but it also occurred in later variants of fuþark.

The older fuþark is popular for modern-day usages of runes (such as video games, tourist souvenirs etc.) because its larger set of characters makes it easier to translate modern English words into runes. However, few inscriptions are preserved in this rune form and it went out of use before the dawn of the Viking Age.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Runes in Anglo-Saxon England and Frisia</title>
<id>anglo_saxon_frisian</id>
<body>Runes were introduced to England in the fifth century, during the Anglo-Saxon invasion of the country.

During <b>the seventh and eight centuries</b>, several more runes were added to the runic alphabet, producing a so-called <b><i>Anglo-Saxon</i>, or <i>Anglo-Frisian futhorc</i></b>.

We call it <i>futhorc</i>, since the new <b>o</b>-rune ᚩ was moved into the fourth position. <i>Futhorc</i> had more runes than the elder futhark, to accommodate for phonetic developments in England and Frisia.

The order and forms of the runes in futhorc were probably established by the end of the 7th century, perhaps thanks to reforms of church scholars.

<img src="learn_anglo_frisian_futhorc">The <i>Anglo-Saxon</i>/<i>Anglo-Frisian futhorc</i>.</img>

Runic writing was most produced in England in eighth and ninth centuries. During the tenth century, runic writing began to be less used for carving, some scribes kept using runic alphabet for manuscripts. The runic manuscripts seem however to belong mostly to antiquarian scholarship.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Younger Fuþark (and the vikings)</title>
<id>younger_futhark</id>
<body>As you know from the last lesson, fuþark expanded from twenty four runes to twenty eight or even more to keep up with the sound changes in spoken Germanic in England and Frisia.

The Scandinavian Germanic sound system also underwent significant changes in the sixth and seventh centuries. The writing system, however, changed drastically in the opposite direction - it was reduced from the older futhark by one-third!

<img src="learn_futhark_reduction">The Scandinavian reduction of the older <i>fuþark</i>.</img>

Apart from dropping eight runes, some of the others got simplified forms. Thus, the <b>younger futhark</b> was born.

<img src="learn_early_younger_futhark">The runes of the earliest younger <i>fuþark</i> inscriptions (ᚺ, ᚼ, ᛗ differ from more mature forms of the row).</img>

An example inscription in the early variant of younger <i>fuþark</i> is the Snoldelev stone, decorated with an iconic picture of three interlaced horns:

<img src="image_snoldelev">The Snoldelev stone (kept in Denmark's National Museum) showcases the early younger futhark forms for <i>a (ᚼ)</i> and <i>h (ᚺ)</i>.</img>

Younger <i>fuþark</i> developed in ninth and tenth centuries into two forms: <i>long-branch</i> and <i>short-twig</i>.

<img src="learn_younger_futhark_long_and_short">The less simplified <i>long-branch</i> younger futhark and the more simplified <i>short-twig</i> younger futhark.</img>

The geographical distributions of inscriptions in both forms are strongly divergent. The <i>long-branch</i> runes were found mostly in Denmark and the <i>short-twig</i> form in Sweden and Norway. However, in eleventh century, the <i>long-branch</i> form became dominant in Sweden too, while Norway adopted a mixed system:

<img src="learn_younger_futhark_mixed">The Norwegian <i>mixed</i> futhark.</img>

It is not known for sure, why <i>younger fuþark</i> emerged from the more complex older system. However it appears to have been a result of a conscious reform, given how drastic and rapid the changes were.
Some simplicity was gained, for example by discarding the hard-to-carve rune <b>ᛞ</b> (<i>/d/</i>) and making <b>ᛏ</b> stand for both <i>/t</i> and <i>/d/</i>. <b>ᚢ</b> became even more multifunctional, standing for <i>/u/, /o/, /y/, /ø/, /w/</i> (after dropping <b>ᛟ</b> <i>/o/</i> and <b>ᚹ</b> <i>/w/</i>).

Younger fuþark is the runic system with the largest number preserved inscriptions to this day. After all, it was the dominant runic system in the <b>Viking Age</b>.

It is no wonder then, that we may find many local variations and experimentation.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>The Jelling stones</title>
<id>jelling_stones</id>
<body><b>Spoiler alert!</b> It is recommended to complete the exercises about Jelling stones (<i>Gorm's stone</i> and <i>Harald's stone</i>) before reading this lesson.

In central Jutland (the peninsula constituting the continental part of Denmark), there's a small town called Jelling. It can be reached by taking a bus from Vejle - the closest larger city - departing every hour or so.

Apart from a supermarket, a few cafes, shops and services, Jelling hosts arguably the most important historical artifact from the Viking Age - the <b>Jelling Monuments</b> raised by <b>the Viking kings, Gorm the Old and his son Harald Bluetooth</b> in the 10th century.

The area consists of two burial mounds, two rune stones, a church, and a gigantic grave marker - a 350-metre-long ship setting; all surrounded by 1.4km long palisade. At the highest point in the landscape, this monument used to be an enormous show of power.

The <b>south mound</b> is 10 meters high and 70 meters wide. Despite excavations, no tomb was found. The <b>north mound</b> is 8.5 meters high and 65 meters wide. In 1820, a tomb built in the winter 958/59 was discovered in the centre of the mound (precise dating thanks to timber dating in the chamber ceiling). The tomb contained precious things, but no skeleton. Could it be that the deceased was later moved from a pagan mound to a church?

More precisely, the deceased in question could have been King Gorm. There is a tomb under the church floor, containing bones of a man - possibly Gorm the Old.

<img src="learn_jelling_church">The <b>Jelling church</b> on the inside. Harald Bluetooth might have had his King's Hall on the same spot, before the church was build.</img>

Speaking of the church, it is surrounded by a small cemetery with two rune stones.

<img src="learn_jelling_stones">The <b>Jelling stones</b>: Gorm's stone (left) and Harald's stone (right).</img>

The smaller of the two is the <b>Gorm's stone</b> with the inscription: <i>King Gorm made this monument to Thyra, his wife, Denmark's adornment</i>.

The larger is <b>Harald's stone</b> adorned with animal motifs, a human figure (Christ?) and a runic inscription: <i>King Harald bade this monument be made in memory of Gorm his father and Thyra his mother, that Harald who won for himself all Denmark and Norway and made the Danes Christians.</i>.

As you remember, the next big city around Jelling is Vejle. If you take a stroll through Strøget - the main/shopping street - pay attention to the pavement. You will see parts of the Jelling stones' inscriptions commemorated under your feet:

<img src="learn_aft_kurm">...<i>aft kurm</i> - <i>after Gorm</i>...</img>
<img src="learn_fadur_sin">...<i>faþur sin</i> - <i>his father</i>...</img>
<img src="learn_aukaft_thaurui">...<i>auk aft þaurui</i> - <i>and after Thyra</i>...</img>
<img src="learn_modur_sin">...<i>moþur sina</i> - <i>his mother</i>...</img>

Sources: plaques in Jelling.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Harald Bluetooth's lost stone</title>
<id>lost_stone</id>
<body>You now know about the <b>Jelling stones</b>, raised by <b>Gorm the Old</b> and <b>Harald Bluetooth</b>. Both of them mention <b>Thyra</b>, wife of Gorm and mother of Harald.

Some 30 kilometers from Jelling there is a 50 tons massive stone <b>Hamborggårdstenen</b>, which, according to the legend, was meant to be the third Jelling stone!

Let us start with a picture:

<img src="learn_lost_stone">Hamborggårdstenen</img>

<b>Hamborggårdstenen</b> is a glaciar boulder. Some 15000 years ago, as the glaciers were retreating north over Scandinavia during <i>Last Glacial Period</i>, they left huge stones, such as this one. The stone is almost 3 metres high and even larger in width, summing up to 20 cubic metres and 50 tons.

According to <b>Saxo Grammaticus'</b> <i>Gesta Danorum</i> (<i>History of the Danes</i>), Harald Bluetooth was trying to get this stone carried to Jelling by his men, to set it up in memory of his mother. But then he heard that his son Svein Forkbeard had rebelled against him, and was forced to leave the stone and flee. A legend also claims that a king in the old days dragged the stone from the North Sea to use it for a memorial.

Notably, there are other Viking-Age monuments worth visiting very close (walking distance!) from Hamborggårdstenen: <b>Klabæk Høje, Bække stone 1 and 2, Læborg stone</b>.

Sources: An information plaque next to the stone. See also: https://www.geus.dk/udforsk-geologien/ture-i-naturen/kaempesten/hamborggaardsstenen/
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Regional differences in rune stone arrangements</title>
<id>regional_differences</id>
<body>Runic inscriptions in Younger Futhark differ in rune form, subject to local variations and shifting trends, as you know from the previous lessons.

Another important difference between Danish and Swedish runestones was the <b>arrangement of the text</b> on the stone.

Consider the Danish stones:

<img src="learn_danish_stones">Examples of some well-known Danish runestones.</img>

and the Swedish ones:

<img src="learn_swedish_stones">Examples of some well-known Swedish runestones.</img>

As you see, the Swedish stones generally were adorned with wormy shapes and animal motifs. Runes were generally written inside these shapes, with occasional additions outside if the carver forgot a word or ran out of space.

Danish stones were inscribed on the wide face of the stone, the text following a clear direction: horizontal, vertical, or a "frame". Runes were carved between even lines.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Ambiguous runes</title>
<id>ambiguous_runes</id>
<body>As you will see from the transliteration exercises (if you haven't already), sometimes the same rune was used to represent different sounds.

A good example is the <b>ᚽ</b> rune, which could stand for either <i>h</i> or <i>e</i>. Compare Eiði runestick from Faroe Islands and the Össeby runestone fragment from Sweden:

<img src="image_eidi_runestick">Here <b>ᚽ</b> stands for <i>h</i>, in the rune row.</img>
<img src="image_osseby_fragment">Here <b>ᚽ</b> stands for <i>e</i>, in the word <b>ᚽᚠᛏᛁᛦ</b> - <i>after</i>.</img>

Consider also the Hobro stone in Denmark and the use of <b>ᛦ</b>-rune on its inscription.

It is first used in its conventional meaning (<i>ʀ</i> in the ending of a masculine name) in the first word <b>ᚦᚢᚱᛁᛦ</b> (<i>Thurir</i>). Later however it represents <i>æ</i> in words <b>ᛏᚱᛦᚴ</b> (<i>træk - guy</i>) and <b>ᚠᛦᛚᛅᚴᛅ</b> (<i>fælaka - friend</i>).

<img src="image_hobro">Hobro stone. Here, the rune <b>ᛦ</b> was used in not only in it's conventional meaning (<i>ʀ</i>), but also to represent <i>æ</i>-sound!</img>

Sources: https://www.mariagerfjordbibliotekerne.dk/runesten
</body>

<lesson>
<title>Medieval runes</title>
<id>medieval_runes</id>
<body>By the 12th century, the roman-alphabet writing was well established in Scandinavia. For some time, while runes were still common, the Scandinavian countries were two-script communities.

The roman alphabet has also made its influence on the medieval runic writing.

For example, when runes are listed in the <i>futhark</i> sequence, the order changes from <b>ml</b> to <b>lm</b>.

By the 13th century, the <b>gemination</b> (doubling) of consonant runes is common to mark the length. For example, <i>þetta</i> (<i>this</i>) replaced the traditional spelling <i>þita</i>/<i>þeta</i>.

The Burseryd font from Småland, Sweden (c. 1300?) has a spelling <b>ᚵᚯᚱᛐᚼᚽ</b> (<i>gørthi</i> - <i>made</i>). Notably, the sound /ð/ is rendered as <b>th</b> rather than <b>þ</b>.

<img src="learn_medieval_futhork">The medieval runes.</img>

The so-called <i>dotted runes</i> (<b>ᚡ, ᚧ, ᚤ, ᚵ, ᛂ, ᛑ, ᛔ</b>) are traditionally transliterated as (respectively) <b>v, ð, y, g, e, d, p</b>. Transliteration with dotted letters is a departure from this standard practice, but it can be useful to show that the characters are derived from their plain counterparts. In this app, we use the traditional transliteration for pragmatic reasons - to use symbols that occur on keyboards.

<img src="learn_dotted_runes_trad">Traditional rendering of the dotted runes.</img>

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Translation</title>
<id>translation</id>
<body>Reading a runic inscription usually consists of two steps: <b>transliteration</b> and <b>translation</b> and we haven't talked about the latter yet.

Most inscriptions are written in Old Norse, which is mostly similar to modern Icelandic and bears similarities to other Germanic languages. Simple memorial stones, after transliteration, are understandable for most Scandinavian speakers, but there are many ways in which the meaning can be obscured:

<b>1. Complex poetic forms.</b> For example, the Karlevi stone in Öland, Sweden, contains a whole stanza written in a poetic form <i>dróttkvætt</i>, filled with <b>kennings</b>.
<b>2. Unintelligible text.</b> For instance, the back of the Bergen stick B 149, contains a runic text which can be transliterated, but seems impossible to render into known words.
<b>3. Unknown interpretations.</b> Tirsted stone ends with ᚦᚬ:ᛅᛚᛁᛦ:ᚢᛁᚴᛁᚴᛅᛦ (<i>and then, all vikings</i>), the meaning of which is unknown.

Sources: museum plaques.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Common words</title>
<id>common_words</id>
<body>Translation of runic texts is hard enough for speakers of Scandinavian languages and thus it's an even bigger challenge for English speakers. In this lesson, we'll take a look at some words and phrases which occur often on rune stones and which are similar enough to their modern English counterparts. Hopefully, that way you will feel a bit less lost reading rune texts.

<b>Stein - Stone</b>
Examples: Bjärby stone Ö 36.

<b>Bruþur - Brother</b>
Examples: Gripsholm Sö 179.

<b>Faþur - Father</b>
Examples: Harald's stone in Jelling, Glenstrup 1.

<b>Muþur - Mother</b>
Examples: Harald's stone in Jelling, Gripsholm Sö 178.

<b>Eftir/Aufti - After</b>
Examples: Gripsholm Sö 178, Uppland stone U 614.

<b>Kuþan - Good</b>
Examples: Glenstrup 2.

Let's also throw in some words which don't have clear English analogues, but are very common:

<b>Sin - His/Her</b>
Examples: Uppland stone U 614, Lerkaka stone.

<b>Kone - Wife</b>
Examples: Gorm stone in Jelling.

<b>Dronning - Queen</b>
Examples: Læborg stone.

<b>Auk - And</b>
Examples: Bække 1, Gripsholm Sö 178.

Sources: museum plaques.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Anundshög</title>
<id>anundshog</id>
<body><b>Spoiler alert!</b> It is recommended to complete the exercise about Vs 13 stone before reading this lesson.

<b>Eriksgata</b>

In the Middle Ages, all newly elected kings in Sweden had to make a journey called Eriksgata.
Since the kings were elected in Uppland, the choice had to be approved by representatives of other
regions. From the 12th century to 1609, all fresh kings travelled with their escorts from the
place of election, the Stone of Mora near Uppsala.

As the road was passing by the Anundshög, most medieval kings visited it on their inauguration
journeys. But what <i>is</i> Anundshög?

<b>Anundshög and stone ships</b>

Anundshög is an area in the Badelunda parish in Västmanland. The name (<i>Anund's mound</i>)
technically refers to the burial mound, which at 9 meters high and 64 meters wide is the tallest
of its kind in Sweden. While not precisely dated, it is believed to go back in time as far as the
6th century!

<img src="learn_anundshog">The view at Anundshög from the inside of a ship setting.</img>

The burial mound is surrounded by four stone ship settings, the largest of which is 53 meters long
and 16 meters wide. According to a document from 17th century, the stones had all fallen down by
then, presumably destroyed by Christians who believed them to be pagan symbols, but in 1932 the
work began to restore them. Today, four out of five original stone ships have been restored.
Each ship has a single round stone exactly in the middle, most likely depicting the mast.

<img src="learn_anundshog_view">The view at ship settings from the burial mound.</img>

The ship settings originate from the first millennium but are difficult to date more precisely.
Two of the four are also the biggest in Sweden!

<img src="image_vs_13">The magnificent runestone Vs 13 standing in the row of monoliths.</img>

Throughout the middle ages, up to 1450s, The Ting took place by the Anundshög.

<b>Runestone: Västmanlands runinskrifter 13</b>

Among the monoliths by the side of the road, there is a runestone (Vs 13) explaining that all the
stones were raised by Folkvid and Vred carved the runes. If you haven't yet, go check out the
exercise to learn more! Or better yet, visit the place if you have a chance - but remember to be
respectful and not disturb the old natural and cultural artifacts.

Sources: info boards provided by the city of Västerås.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Sigurdristningen</title>
<id>sigurdristiningen</id>
<body>
<i>Sigurdristningen</i> is one of the largest and most picturesque rune carvings. It's located in Sundbyholm in the Eskilstuna municipality, with runes and pictures carved in a large stone slab by the side of the road. It's known not so much for its text inscription, which follows a pretty standard formula, but rather for its depiction of the saga of Sigurd <i>Fafnesbane</i> (Sigurd the Dragon Slayer).

<img src="learn_sigurdristningen">The Sigurd carving. The photo doesn't even fit all of it!</img>

<b>Sigurd Fafnesbanes saga depiction</b>

If you haven't heard the Sigurd's saga yet, the best source to read it is probably the <i>Poetic Edda</i>. Translations by Carolyne Larrington and Jackson Crawford are among the most popular. We won't summarize it here out of risk of not doing it justice.

How many figures from the Sigurd's saga can you recognize? Click the question marks on the images if you need a hint!

<img src="learn_sigurd_slays_dragon">Sigurd slays the dragon Fafnir</img>

<img src="learn_sigurd_burns_finger">Sigurd burns his finger on Fafnir's heart and puts it in his mouth.</img>

<img src="learn_bird">After tasting Fafnir's blood, Sigurd can now understand birds. The birds warn him that Regin intends to kill him both in revenge and to steal the gold.</img>

<img src="learn_regin_dead">Regin gets killed by Sigurd.</img>

<b>Inscription</b>

The runic inscription runs:

ᛋᛁᚱᛁᚦᚱ ᚴᚬᚱᚦᛁ ᛒᚢᚱ ᚦᚬᛋᛁ ᛘᚢᚦᛁᛦ ᛅᛚᚱᛁᚴᛋ ᛏᚢᛏᛁᛦ ᚢᚱᛘᛋ ᚠᚢᚱ ᛋᛅᛚᚢ ᚼᚢᛚᛘᚴᛁᚱᛋ ᚠᛅᚦᚢᚱ ᛋᚢᚴᚱᚢᚦᛅᚱ ᛒᚢᛅᛏᛅ ᛋᛁᛋ

That translates to modern Swedish as: <i>Sigrid gjorde denna bro, Alriks moder Orms dotter, för själen Holmgers Sigröds fader hennes make</i>. This tells us of a woman named Sigrid, who had a bridge built in memory of her husband Holmger. Also mentioned by name are her sone Alrik, her father Orm, and her stepson Sigröd.

<b>How is Sigurd relevant to the runic text?</b>

It's a mystery why this motif was chosen for ornamentation of the runic inscription. Perhaps it was just the name similarity between Sigröd and Sigurd. Maybe the family wanted to claim relationship to the mythical hero.

Sources: info boards on site provided by Södermanland's museum and Eskilstuna's museums.
</body>
</lesson>