<lesson>
<title>What are runes?</title>
<id>what_are_runes</id>
<body>Runes are an <b>alphabetic writing system</b>, popularly (and for the most part, correctly) associated with Scandinavian culture and with the Viking Age (c. 750-1050).

Though in principle runes may be used to write in any language, they are best suited to record the sounds of old Germanic tongues.

Unlike other European scripts (roman or greek alphabets, cyrillic letters), runes are an <b>epigraphic</b> script. In other words, they were normally carved into stone, wood, metal or bone, rather than written on paper. Of course, runic manuscripts do exist, but they were produced later, from historical curiosity.

<img src="image_gardby_runsten">Runestones were often raised to commemorate deceased family members</img>

It is important to emphasize that there wasn't a single canonical runic alphabet and the scripts varied depending on both geographical and temporal dimensions.

Commonly, four main types of rune row are distinguished: <b>the older fuþark, the Anglo-Frisian fuþorc, the younger fuþark and the medieval fuþork</b>. They differed in the number of symbols, complexity and the set of expressible sounds. Even within these four types, countless local variations are found.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Futhark? Fuþark? Fuþork?</title>
<id>futhark_meaning</id>
<body><b><i>Futhark, fuþark, fuþork...</i></b> what <i>are</i> those?

As you probably know very well, the word <i>alphabet</i> originates from the first two letters of the latin alphabet: <i>alpha (α)</i> and <i>beta (β)</i>.

It's exactly the same story with the runic alphabets. The name <i>futhark</i> comes from the first six runes in the rune row: <b>ᚠ (f), ᚢ (u), ᚦ (þ/th), ᚨ (a), ᚱ (r), ᚲ (k)</b>. As you can see, <i>futhark</i> and <i>fuþark</i> are different renderings, depending on how one chooses to read the Thorn rune (ᚦ).

<i>Fuþorc</i> is a rendering of the first characters of the <b>Anglo-Frisian</b> rune row (<b>ᚠᚢᚦᚩᚱᚳ</b>), and <i>fuþork</i> of the so-called (Scandinavian) medieval rune row (<b>ᚠᚢᚦᚮᚱᚴ</b>).

<img src="learn_futhark_6_runes">Comparison of first 6 runes</img>

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Transliteration</title>
<id>transliteration</id>
<body>Runic inscriptions are often presented in <b>transliteration</b>.

Every rune is assigned a corresponding letter from modern alphabet, generally roman, but also regional European letters as well as IPA characters are used.

Let us start with an example - the model for transliterating the older fuþark:

<img src="learn_older_futhark">The older <i>fuþark</i></img>

The modern equivalents for runic characters are generally chosen based on supposed sound value, but scholars accept that perfect phonetic reproduction of Viking Age language is impossible. Moreover, one rune can denote multiple sounds. For example: <i>ᚢ</i> may stand for <i>u</i>, <i>v</i>, and others, depending on the context.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>Where did runes come from?</title>
<id>origins</id>
<body>The oldest known runic writings date back to at least the second century AD.

The earliest documented runic artifacts generally come from the area of modern Denmark, southern Norway and southern Sweden, however a number has been also found in northern Germany and eastern Europe.

The development of the runes was most likely influenced by contacts with the Roman Empire. Scholars have also emphasized striking similarities between the runic and other Mediterranean writing systems (Phoenician, Greek, Etruscan). Observation of literary societies inspired Germanic speakers to imitate this form of communication.

Despite developing their own writing system, the Germanic people cultivated mainly oral traditions for many centuries to come and never succeeded in introducing a wide-scale literacy (or perhaps never intended to). The first inscriptions were extremely laconic and consisted chiefly of names.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>

<lesson>
<title>The older fuþark</title>
<id>the_older_futhark</id>
<body>The <b>older fuþark</b> is the oldest known rune row. We say <b>rune row</b> somewhat interchangeably with <i>alphabet</i>, but also to stress the differences between rune rows and Greek and Roman alphabets. The order of the symbols is completely different from the Mediterranean alphabets, though the reason for this phenomenon is not known for sure.

<img src="learn_older_futhark">The older <i>fuþark</i></img>

We know the order from a number of rune-row inscriptions dated to 5th and 6th centuries. From 11 such inscriptions, only 4 contain the complete older fuþark. One of them is presented below:

<img src="image_kylverstone">The Kylver stone (held in Historiska Museet in Stockholm) depicts the complete older fuþark.</img>

The fuþark was also sometimes divided into three groups of eight symbols, these groups being called <b><i>ættir</i></b> in later Icelandic manuscripts. We don't know the reason for this division, but it also occurred in later variants of fuþark.

The older fuþark is popular for modern-day usages of runes (such as video games, tourist souvenirs etc.) because its larger set of characters makes it easier to translate modern English words into runes. However, few inscriptions are preserved in this rune form and it went out of use before the dawn of the Viking Age.

Sources: <i>Runes: A Handbook</i> by Michael P. Barnes and <i>Runes</i> by Martin Findell.
</body>
</lesson>